Mazur, Jay papers 6036/082
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Jay Mazur papers
1967-2014
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Mazur, Jay
6036/082
3 cubic feet
3 linear ft.
Records.
The collection contains some articles, clippings, correspondence, reports and speeches during Jay Mazur's tenure as ILGWU president and UNITE president.
9447729
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
Jay Mazur was the last president of the ILGWU, serving from 1986 to 1995.
After graduating from high school in 1951, Mazur began work in the Health and Welfare Department of New York City's dressmaker's Local 22. In 1955, Mazur entered the ILGWU's Training Institute, a 1-year intensive program to prepare students for staff appointments in the ILGWU, and was assigned as an organizer in the Upper South Department and the New England Region. After graduation in 1956, Mazur was assigned to Local 40, where he became Director of Organization and Education.
In 1959, Mazur began working for Local 23, which later merged with Local 25 to become Local 23-25. Mazur began work as an organizer for the local in 1959, was elected as Assistant Manager in 1964, and manager in 1973. He became a Vice-President of the International in 1977. During his tenure in Local 23 and 23-25, Mazur was involved in major organizing efforts, as well as significant social and educational programs for union members. He was manager of Local 23-25 in 1982, when thousands of workers in New York City's Chinatown went on strike to win a fair contract. Under his leadership, Local 23-25 established an Immigration Project to assist members and their families with legal and related immigration issues. While working for the union, Mazur earned his an undergraduate degree in Personnel and Labor Studies from City College of New York, and later a master's degree in Labor Studies from Rutgers University.
In 1983, Mazur was elected to the International's leadership as Secretary-Treasurer, and in 1986, he was elected to succeed Sol Chaikin as President of the ILGWU. During his tenure as President, Mazur led major campaigns to stem the decline of garment manufacturing in the United States. This included the creation of the ILGWU's Professional and Clerical Employees (PACE) Division and the Metro Organizing Department, the expansion of the Immigration Project to be national in scope, and the establishment of workers centers in major metropolitan centers. Mazur served on the Executive Councils of the AFL-CIO, and the AFL-CIO's Industrial Union Department of the AFL-CIO; in addition to his work in domestic and international labor federations, he has also served on numerous foundation boards and government commissions.
Under Mazur's leadership, the ILGUW merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers of America to form the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE) in 1995. He served as the first president of UNITE, from 1995 until his retirement in 2001.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains some articles, clippings, correspondence, reports and speeches during Jay Mazur's tenure as ILGWU president and UNITE president. The bulk of the collection details the merger of the ILGWU with ACTWU documenting the preparations that took place between the two organizations.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives 227 Ives Hall Tower Road Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheelref@cornell.edu https://catherwood.library.cornell.edu/kheel/
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, June 20, 2014
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, October 30, 2015
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 6200: UNITE HERE Records
Textile industry -- New York (State); Textile workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State); Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State); Clothing trade -- Labor unions -- New York (State); Mazur, Jay.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees
9447729
- Articles, 1989-2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Attitude Survey of Local 23-25 Members, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Clippings, 2003-2006 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Speeches, 1990-2001 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- UNITE Merger, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- UNITE Merger, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  January-March
- UNITE Merger, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  April-May
- UNITE Merger, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  June-July
- UNITE Merger, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  August-December
- UNITE Merger, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  February-October
- UNITE Merger, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  November
- UNITE Merger, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  December
- UNITE Merger, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  January-February
- UNITE Merger, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  March-April
- UNITE Merger, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  May-July
- UNITE Merger PR, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- UNITE Merger, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- UNITE Merger, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- UNITE, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- UNITE Merger (Box 2, Folder 16)
  undated
- Restricted (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Closed until 2021
- Restricted (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Letters from President Johnson to David Dubinsky, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- News Clippings, 1986-2014 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- A Comprehensive Approach to New York City Apparel Manufacturing Development, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Jay Mazur: A Proposal to Promote New York City's Fashion Industry, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Jay Mazur Speeches, 1990-2007 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- ILGWU 41st Convention Jay Mazur Acceptance Speech, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- American Labor ORT Tribute to Evelyn Dubrow, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- ACTWU Constitution, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- ILGWU Commitment to Apparel Industry Competitiveness, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- New York City is Fashion, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1994-2009 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- ACTWU-ILGWU Merger, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- ACTWU-ILGWU Merger Agreement Arrotation, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Harold Ickes to Jack Sheinkman and Jay Mazur, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Better News Clippings, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- General Executive Board Minutes, 1995-2000 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Sweatshops, 1995-2001 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Amendment to ILGWU Constitution, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Apparel Industry Partnership (AIP), 1998 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Opt-out Battle: ILGWU vs. ACTWU, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Transcript of Lois Gray Interview of Evelyn Dubrow, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Agreement with New York Skirt and Sportswear Association, 2001-2004 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Cuba, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Advisory Committee for Trade Policy and Negotiations (ACTPN), 2002 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Remarks by Jay Mazur on Maida Springer-Kemp, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 25)
- Charles Ranger to Jay Mazur, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Additional Material: UNITE vs. HERE, 2009 (Box 5, Folder 27)
- UNITE Distinguished Scholar Award for FIT, 2010 (Box 5, Folder 28)
- The Evolution of the Jewish Garment Industry 1840-1940, 2012 (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Julius G. Getman: Battling for the Soul of Organized Labor (Box 5, Folder 30)
- Talking Points, March 21 Meeting with John Dyson, Rudy Washington (Box 5, Folder 31)